Guide to the Merrill G. Burlingame Papers 1956-1976
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Merrill G. Burlingame Papers
1956-1976
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2057, MtBC, us
Burlingame, Merrill G. (Merrill Gildea), 1901-1994
5 folders
The Merrill G. Burlingame Papers consist of correspondence between Merrill G. Burlingame and the law firm of Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, handwritten research notes and a folder of related printed materials, clippings, and maps.
Historical Note
Merrill G. Burlingame (1901-1994) was a history professor at Montana State University. In 1956 the law firm of Wilkinson, Cragun, Barker and Hawkins retained his services as a historical researcher for their litigation against the United States government on behalf of Montana's Blackfeet tribe. Burlingame assisted the firm by gathering pertinent materials from his research. By the summer of 1975, the firm was known as Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker and they asked Burlingame, in his capacity as their historical advisor, to give his advice and criticism of research materials they planned to use in a hearing before the United States Indian Claims Commission.
The papers consist primarily of correspondence between Merrill G. Burlingame and the law firm of Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker. The earliest letters, from 1956 to 1957, are largely contractual in nature, specifying the payment and duties expected of Burlingame by the law firm, although some historical evidence analysis is discussed. The letters from 1975-1976 concern critiques of manuscripts prepared by Michael F. Foley on the administration of the Fort Belknap and Blackfeet Indian reservations by the United States government, 1855-1950s. These manuscripts were prepared for the law firm as evidence for the plaintiffs in forthcoming hearing before the Indian Claims Commission. The collection also includes a folder of Burlingame's handwritten research notes and a folder of related printed materials, clippings, and maps.
This collection is open for research.
One folder of letters was donated to Special Collections by Merrill G. Burlingame sometime after 1976. The letters were maintained in a separate file and not incorporated into Burlingame's main collection of papers processed as Collection 2245. An additional folder of relevant materials, previously designated as Collection 732, was incorporated with these materials on October 17, 2011. This collection was reported to the National Union Catalog of Manuscript Collections in 1979 and assigned number 79-630.
Foley, Michael F.
United States-Indian Claims Commission; Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker; Wilkinson, Cragun, Barker and Hawkins
Blackfeet Indian Reservation (Mont.); Fort Belknap Indian Reservation (Mont.)
Indian reservations-Montana; Sihasapa Indians-Montana; Sihasapa Indians-Montana-Claims; Sihasapa Indians-Montana-Government relations
Native Americans; Montana; Maps
- Correspondence, 1956 (Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1957 (Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 3)
  - Letter: Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, to Dr. Merrill G. Burlingame, July 18, 1975; 1
  - Letter: Merrill G. Burlingame to Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, July 22, 1975; 2
    (file copy)
  - Letter: Merrill G. Burlingame to Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, July 23, 1975; 3
  - Letter: Merrill G. Burlingame to Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, July 28, 1975; 4
  - Letter: Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, to Dr. Merrill G. Burlingame, July 31, 1975; 5
  - Letter: Patricia L. Brown for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, to Dr. Merrill G. Burlingame, August 2, 1975; 6
  - Letter: Merrill G. Burlingame to Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, August 8, 1975; 7
  - Letter: Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, to Dr. Merrill G. Burlingame, August 25, 1975; 8
  - Letter: Merrill G. Burlingame to Jerry C. Straus for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, August 30, 1975; 9
  - Letter: Patricia L. Brown for Wilkinson, Cragun and Barker, to Dr. Merrill G. Burlingame, February 24, 1976; 10
  - Photocopies of covers of two Michael F. Foley monographs, 11
  - Copy of defendant's exhibit FB-577, Errata - Before the Indian Claims Commission, 12
- Handwritten notes (Folder 4)
- Clippings, maps, printed reports (Folder 5)